Guide to the New York State Teachers Association Records 1915-1979
New York State Teachers Association Records
- Series III: Executive Secretary's Files
  - Sub-Series C: Goold Subject Files, 1950-1971, 1950-1971
    - Sub-Series c: Other Organizations, 1934-1970
      - NYS Dental Hygiene Teachers' Assn., 1957-1963 (Box 45, Folder 14)
        Contains a copy of association bylaws and constitution, correspondence, a news clipping re a resolution of NYS School Boards Assn. proposing that dental hygiene teachers no longer be classed as teachers, which would eliminate them from coverage under the present pay scale for teachers. 1957-63
      - NYS Department of Labor, 1961 (Box 45, Folder 15)
        Contains a copy of the e Labor Management Improper Practices Act and correspondence dealing with whether or not NYSTA was covered under the definition of labor organization. 1961
      - NYS Division for Youth, 1966 (Box 45, Folder 16)
        Contains various reports of the Governor's Conference on Children and Youth, and a report on the American Lower Class Family, as well as data on youth. Also contains a report of youth and work training project-Action Phase, and a pamphlet on youth and work training "A Model Project" 1966
      - NYS Division for Youth, 1966 (Box 45, Folder 17)
        Continuation. 1966
      - NYS Driver and Safety Educators. 1967 (Box 45, Folder 18)
      - NYS Employees Retirement System, 1965-1966 (Box 45, Folder 19)
        Contains copies of bills pertaining to the retirement system and a brief description of a study of the Teachers Retirement System by Dean David G. Moor of NYSSILR. 1965-66
      - NYS Institution Educators Assoc., 1963-1964 (Box 45, Folder 20)
        Contains salary information and correspondence re efforts to extend the public school calendar to institution teachers. 1963-64
      - NYS Institution Educators Assoc., 1965-1966 (Box 45, Folder 21)
        Contains memos and correspondence outlining efforts to the reasons for revision of Institution Educators' salary. Also contains statements by Goold and the NYSIEA's president Francis Johnson, on behalf of the pay hike and brief in support of the raise, a memo outlining NYSTA's reasons for involvement with NYSIEA is also included. 1965,66
      - NYS Joint Legislative Committee on Industrial and Labor Conditions, 1964-1966 (Box 45, Folder 22)
        Contains memo re amendment of the Condin-Waldin Act, an act amending the civil service law in relation to strike and public employee labor relations programs, and another memo re employee relations in public employment 1964, 65, 66
      - NYS Joint Legislative Committee on Practices and Procedures-1958(Paul Talbot, Chairman) (Box 45, Folder 23)
        Contains a letter notifying NYSTA of a public hearing on legislative practices and procedures. 1958
      - NYS Retired Teacher's Association, 1954 (Box 45, Folder 24)
        Contains newsletters and correspondence re legislation. 1954
      - NYS Retired Teachers Association, 1960-1963 (Box 45, Folder 25)
        Contains general correspondence, comments on the status of the invitation of the NYSTA to the NYSRTA to become a division of the NYSTA, and a certificate of incorporation by-law rules and regulations. 1960-61-62-63
      - NYS Retired Teachers Assoc., 1960-1961 (Box 45, Folder 26)
        Committee re Division NYSTA. Contains correspondence and reports about NYSRTA's affiliation with NYSTA. 1960-61
      - NYS School Boards Assoc., 1956 (Box 45, Folder 27)
        Contains a statement by Everett Dyer, Assoc. President, at a budget hearing a summary of the Heald Commission Report dealing with school finance, a summary of the annual convention of the NYS School Boards Assoc., and a report on a symposium of the Assc. On the problems of public education. 1956
      - NYS Schools Boards Assoc., 1961 (Box 45, Folder 28)
        Contains a report on federal support of public education and memos and bills which constituted the Assoc.'s legislative program. 1961
      - NYS School Boards Assoc. (Box 45, Folder 29)
        Contains memos and bills dealing with apportionment of state aid, conference expenses, and local indebtedness and take home pay, and a copy of NYSTA News outlining NYSTA's legislative program. Also contains a memo on merit rating and teachers salaries. A report on the NYS Municipal situation (Financial), and correspondence concerning teacher-school board relations, legislation and establishment of grievance procedures. News clippings dealing with state and federal aid to education are also included. 1962
      - NYS School Boards Assn., 1962 (Box 46, Folder 1)
        Newsletter. 1962
      - NYS School Boards Assn., 1963 (Box 46, Folder 2)
        Contains news clippings dealing with the Assn.'s stand on off-track betting and state aid to education, and a bill of particular dealing with local control in public education. Also contains copies of bills and memos which comprised and legislative program of the Assn. for 1963, correspondence between Goold Everett Dyer, Exec. Dir. Of NYSSBA, re professional practices, and a bill and memo from NYSTA re professional rights and responsibilities. 1963
      - NYSSBA, 1964 (Box 46, Folder 3)
        Contains bills and memos comprising the Assn.'s legislative program, correspondence re NYSTA-NYSSBA disputes over 5% bill legislation, and an article by Goold dealing with the role of the teacher, and a copy and interpretation of the code of ethics for teachers. Also contains a brief survey dealing with school board satisfaction with budgetary authority. 1964
      - NYSSBA, 1964-1965 (Box 46, Folder 4)
        Newsletter. 1964, 65
      - NYSSBA, 1964-1965 (Box 46, Folder 5)
        Research Bulletins, 1964-65
      - NYSSBA, 1965 (Box 46, Folder 6)
        Report of 46th Annual Convention, Syracuse N.Y. Oct. 24-26, 1965
      - NYSSBA, 1965 (Box 46, Folder 7)
        1965 proposals, routine correspondence
      - NYSSBA, 1966 (Box 46, Folder 8)
        Contains a news clipping dealing with State Education Commissioner Allen's stand on church-state issue with regards to aid to education. Also contains a letter to Anthony Travia-Speaker of the NYS Assembly-from Everett Dyer, Exec. Dir. Of NYSSBA, dealing with the Educational Conference Board Bill, and a position statement on public employee relations. A brief clipping explaining the tax deferred annuity program is also included. 1966
      - NYSSBA. Legislative Program., 1966 (Box 46, Folder 9)
        Contains the legislative program for the Assn. 1966
      - NYS School Board Assn.-Research Services, 1966 (Box 46, Folder 10)
        Contains a report on school board-staff relations by Prof. Robert Doherty, NYSSILR, and a report on the purchasing power of t he dollar, and programs for the mentally retarded. Also a memo alluding to further reports of school board-staff relations by Prof. G. Brooks, NYSSILR. 1966
      - NYSSBA-Constitutional Convention, 1967 (Box 46, Folder 11)
        Contains a statement in support of the NYSSBA position, in opposition to adoption of the NYS Constitution. 1967
      - NYS School-Nurse Teacher Assn., 1956 (Box 46, Folder 12)
        Contains a chronological history of how the Nurse Teachers defeated a bill that would have merged them with county health units. 1956
      - NYS School Nurse Teachers Assn. 1956 (Box 46, Folder 13)
      - NYS School Nurse Teachers Assn., 1957-1958 (Box 46, Folder 14)
        Contains general correspondence and the organizations constitution. 1957-58
      - NYS School Nurse Teachers Assn., 1962-1965 (Box 46, Folder 15)
        Contains correspondence dealing with illegal employment of unqualified persons to serve as nurse-teachers, a copy of the decision in the Northport case involving the issue of illegal employment, and a review of status problems of school nurse-teachers. 1962-63, 1964-65
      - NYS School Nurse Teachers Assn., 1964 (Box 46, Folder 16)
        Contains miscellaneous information, routine correspondence, Northport case 1/9/64 re illegal employment of nurse-teachers.
      - NYS School Nurse Teachers Assn., 1964 (Box 46, Folder 17)
      - NYS School Nurse Teachers Assn., 1964 (Box 46, Folder 18)
      - NYS School Nurse Teachers Ass., 1964 (Box 46, Folder 19)
      - NYSSNTA, 1966 (Box 46, Folder 20)
        Contains a report by the council for Administrative Leadership on Nurses in the Schools, a statement of the Assn.'s president, Marjorie Norcross, regarding amendment of the Education Law as it pertains to employment of Nurse Teachers, and correspondence re an ethical argument re duties in Wheatland-Chili school district, 1966
      - NYS Science Teachers Assn., 1964-1965 (Box 46, Folder 21)
        Resolutions, 1964-65
      - NYS Teachers Retirement Board, 1944 (Box 46, Folder 22)
        Contains a report of meeting of delegates to the retirement system, and reports of the Retirement Committee to the Board of Directors. 1944-
      - NYS Teachers Retirement Board Bulletin. 1966 (Box 46, Folder 23)
      - NYS Teachers Retirement Board, 1947-1954 (Box 46, Folder 24)
        Contains general correspondence, a pamphlet dealing with the legal aspects of t he teachers retirement system, and correspondence re legislation pertinent to retirement. 1947-54 cumulative.
      - NYSTRS, 1956 (Box 46, Folder 25)
        Contains copies of the teachers' retirement law. 1956
      - NYSTRS, 1960-1961 (Box 46, Folder 26)
        Contains general correspondence, the annual report, and a pamphlet on prior service. 1960-61
      - NYSTRS, 1962-1963 (Box 46, Folder 27)
        Contains statistical data, correspondence re various legislative bills, and correspondence and enwsclippings related to complains about the retirement system. 1962-63
      - NYSTRS-Data, 1962 (Box 46, Folder 28)
        Contains statistical information as well as legal information regarding the plan. 1962
      - NYSTRS-Booklets, Brochures, and Annual Report. 1964 (Box 46, Folder 29)
      - NYSTRS, 1964 (Box 46, Folder 30)
        Herald Tribune articles re an investigation of the retirement system. 1964
      - NYSTRS, 1964 (Box 46, Folder 31)
        Contains correspondence re charges of mismanagement of the system. 1964
      - NYSTRS, 1964 (Box 46, Folder 32)
        Contains statement by Goold and Balassone, president of NYSTA, re the controversy. 1964
      - NYSTRS, 1966 (Box 46, Folder 33)
        Contains annual report for 1966, a comparison of the state teachers, state employees, and City Teachers Retirement Systems, and a NYSTA statement re the Insurance Department's report on NYSTRS. 1966
      - NYSTRS-Candidates for Retirement Boards, 1966 (Box 46, Folder 34)
        Contains minutes of a Retirement Meeting outlining a confrontation with Ellis Ostgrave and Muriel Weber, NYSTA candidate for NYSTRS. Also contains Ostrave's analysis of the 5% Pay Plan, and a checklist of problems and projects for attention of NYSTRS. 1966
      - NYSTRS-Delegates to System, 1966 (Box 46, Folder 35)
        Contains lists of delegates and a special memo from NYSTA re the election of teacher members to the Retirement Board. 1966
      - NYS Teachers Retirement System, 1966 (Box 46, Folder 36)
        Contains Ostrove reports on Meetings of Tri-County Teachers Retirement Council. 1966
      - NYSTRS, 1967 (Box 46, Folder 37)
        Contains general correspondence, correspondence concerning interest and contribution rates as well as election of members to the Retirement Board, a pamphlet on variable annuity, and an outline of legislation affecting NYSTRS. 1967
      - NYSTRS. Account reports. 1967 (Box 46, Folder 38)
      - NYSTRS. Bulletins. 1967 (Box 46, Folder 39)
      - NYSTRS, 1967 (Box 46, Folder 40)
        Contains correspondence re Ostrava's criticism of NYSTRS, and correspondence re the election of delegates to the Retirement Board. 1967
      - NYSTR, 1967 (Box 46, Folder 41)
        Contains correspondence and memos dealing with revisions of NYSTRS. May 11, 1967
      - NYSTRS-Minutes. 1967 (Box 47, Folder 1)
      - NYSTRS-Minutes. 1967 (Box 47, Folder 2)
      - NYSTRS. Bulletins, Newsletters. 1968 (Box 47, Folder 3)
      - NYSTRS, 1968 (Box 47, Folder 4)
        Contains lists of delegates to the NYSTRS and the platform of John Gardner-NYSTA candidate for the Retirement Board. 1968
      - NYSTRS, 1968 (Box 47, Folder 5)
        Ostrove Reports on meetings of Tri-County Teachers Retirement Council. 1968
      - NYS Vocational and Practical Arts Association, 1948-1954 (Box 47, Folder 6)
        contains general correspondence. 1948- 54
      - NY Teachers Guild (NYC), 1959 (Box 47, Folder 7)
        Contains newsletters and a brief in support of the extension of psychological services to the NYC Public Schools, and an increase in the salaries of psychologists employed b the Boards of Education of NYC. 1959
      - Northeastern State Secretaries, 1964 (Box 47, Folder 8)
        Routine correspondence re arranging meetings. 1964
      - Northeastern State Secretaries, 1965 (Box 47, Folder 9)
        Routine correspondence arranging meetings. 3/18/65
      - Northeaster State Secretaries, 1965 (Box 47, Folder 10)
        Meeting 5/20-20/65 re leadership, agenda, routine correspondence
      - Northeastern State Secretaries (Executive Secretaries of State Teachers Assn. Northeast Region), 1965 (Box 47, Folder 11)
        Routine correspondence re meeting at Conn. Education Assn. Headquarters in Hartford, Nov. 34, 1965
      - Public Education Assn., 1961-1963 (Box 47, Folder 12)
        Contains press releases and general information leaflets. Also contains a memo dealing with financial problems of big cities, and a statement by Dr. Frederick C. McLaughlin, Director of the Assn., before the Joint Legislative Committee on School Financing. 1961-63
      - State Affiliates, 1968-1969 (Box 47, Folder 13)
        Contains reports of various affiliates plus a listing of NYSTA affiliates. 1968-69
      - State Affiliates. 1968-69, 1968-1969 (Box 47, Folder 14)
      - State Education Department-General. 1961 (Box 47, Folder 15)
      - State Education Department-General, 1961 (Box 47, Folder 16)
        Contains information on financing and regents exams. 1961
      - SED-General, 1962 (Box 47, Folder 17)
        Contains a memo dealing with expenditures per pupil in average daily attendance, a report on a racial census of elementary school pupils, a memo outlining standards for good schools, and a sires of acts dealign with the powers of Boards of Education, and superintendents, and the city school system of NYC. 1962
      - SED-General (Box 47, Folder 18)
        Contains a pamphlet dealing with the Statewide Conference on Physical Fitness in institutions of higher education, and pamphlets dealing with education statistics. 1962-63, 63-64
      - SED-General. 1964 (Box 47, Folder 19)
      - SED-General. 1967 (Box 47, Folder 20)
      - SED-Advisory Committee, 1957 (Box 47, Folder 21)
        Contains memos on reorganization. 1957
      - SED Advisory Committee, 1957 (Box 47, Folder 22)
        Contains an analysis of existing school districts and the need for their reorganization, a report by the Subcommittee on Size of School Districts information dealing with school enrollment, a report re criteria that may be used to determine the size of an efficient secondary school unit. 1957
      - SED Advisory Council, 1968 (Box 47, Folder 23)
        Contains general correspondence 1968
      - SED to Board of Regents re Secondary Certification, 1957 (Box 47, Folder 24)
        Contains statement from NYSTA to the Regents. 1957
      - SED Boards of Regents Registration of Teacher Assns. 1961 (Box 47, Folder 25)
      - SED Board of Regents Legislation Assignment of Pupils to Schools, 1964 (Box 47, Folder 26)
        Contains a statement by Regents and a news clipping re involuntary transfer of students on racial grounds. 1964
      - SED Board of Regents-Urban Education (State Aid), 1967-1968 (Box 47, Folder 27)
        Contains guidelines for urban education as well as a summary of the Regent's Urban Education Proposal. 1967-68
      - SED Board of Regents-Candidates. 1968 (Box 47, Folder 28)
      - SED Board of Regents, 1969 (Box 47, Folder 29)
      - SED Board of Regents, 1969 (Box 47, Folder 30)
        Contains legislative recommendations and the statement of NYSTA President Catherine Barrett. 1969
      - SED Board of Regents, 1969 (Box 47, Folder 31)
        Legislative Hearing 9/5/59. Contains the statement of NYSTA and general correspondence. 1969
      - SED Board of Regents-Legislation, 1970 (Box 47, Folder 32)
        Contains legislative recommendations of the regents and the statement of NYSTA President Catharine Barrett to the Regents. 1970
      - SED Bureau of Teacher Education and Certification, 1961 (Box 47, Folder 33)
        Contains proposed guidelines for state approval of preparation programs for teachers of secondary science and mathematics and general correspondence. 1961
      - SED Bureau of Teacher Education and Certification. 1962 (Box 47, Folder 34)
      - SED Bureau of Teacher Education. 1963 (Box 47, Folder 35)
      - SED Bureau of Teacher Education and Certification, 1966 (Box 47, Folder 36)
        General Information. 1966
      - SED-Certification Requirements Administrative and Supervisory Positions, 1965 (Box 47, Folder 37)
        contains a draft of certification requirements and the recommendations of TEPS committee regarding the draft. 1965
      - SED Bureau of Teacher Education an Certification n.d. (Box 47, Folder 38)
      - SED Bureau of Teacher Education and Certification., 1961 (Box 47, Folder 39)
        Certification of teacher aides. 1961
      - SED-Coding and Classification Committee, 1960-1962 (Box 48, Folder 1)
        Contains general correspondence and budgets for the Great Neck Public Schools. 1960-62
      - SED-Coding and Classification Committee, 1960-1962 (Box 48, Folder 2)
        Contains committee minutes, reactions to the NYS Classification and Coding Study, principles to serve as a guide for the development of a new coding and classification, a report of the NYS Study of Coding and Classification for School Financial Accounting, and a manual of instructions for the classification of receipts and disbursements for public schools in NYS. 1960-62
      - SED-Commissioner, 1951 (Box 48, Folder 3)
        Contains general correspondence and news clippings dealing with a dispute over teachers' duties with regard to extracurricular activities. 1951
      - SED Commissioner, 1961 (Box 48, Folder 4)
        Contains correspondence involving discrimination at Queens College, and new clippings dealing with charges made by Long Island Federation of Teachers that Allen was anti-labor. Also contains a memo from the commissioner to the Board of Regents re goals for education in NYS. 1961
      - SED-Commissioner (Box 48, Folder 5)
        Contains a report on the operation of NYC Schools, recommendations by the Regents and the commissioner pertaining to the organization and administration of the City School District of NYC, and the Interim Report of the Board of Education of NYC re organization and administration, Also contains a position statement of the Regents dealing with federal aid for public elementary and secondary education, comments by the Allen on trade and industrial education, the Diefednorf committee, a memo dealing with the creation of an advisory board on teacher education, to the NYS Superintendents. A copy of the certification requirements for elementary teachers, and news clippings dealing with integration and federal aid are included. 1962
      - SED Commissioner, 1962 (Box 48, Folder 6)
        Contains a decision re certification. 1962
      - SED Commissioner (Box 48, Folder 7)
        Contains comments from Allen's Grossinger Speech where he discussed the interim report of the Joint Legislative Committee on School Financing, and a statement by Allen before the Senate Subcommittee on Education, memos on racial imbalance in public schools, and a speech discussing the educational hierarchy in NYS. Also contains a letter to Dr. Gross, Superintendent of Schools for Brooklyn, re the Board of Education's plan for integration, and the major legislative proposals of the Regents. News clippings re state aid to education and racial imbalance are also included. 1963
      - SED Commissioner, 1964 (Box 48, Folder 8)
        Contains news clippings dealing with the 1965 legislative program, correspondence to Gov. Rockefeller dealing with integration and unemployment, a policy statement from Goold re teacher-school board relations, and correspondence re evaluation of teacher aids. 1964
      - SED-James E. Allen, Jr., Commissioner of Education, SUNY., 1969 (Box 48, Folder 9)
      - SED-Commissioner's Conference, May 8, 1964 (Box 48, Folder 10)
        Contains general correspondence re the 1964 legislative session and news clippings dealing with proposals for 1965. 1964
      - SED-Commissioner's Decisions, 1955-1958 (Box 48, Folder 11)
        Contains cases dealing with tenure, transportation, religious materials in classrooms, accusations of communist party membership, use of school buildings by outside organizations, and the powers of the Board of Examiners of NYC. 1955-58
      - SED-Commissioners Decisions, 1959-1965 (Box 48, Folder 12)
        Contains cases dealing with dress codes, the rights of the union to used school facilities, salary rights, t he employment of registered nurses, grievance rights with regard to choice of representative, opening daily exercises, a representational election involving the Teachers' Union of the City of NY, and charges of communist affiliation. 1959-65
      - SED-Commissioner's Decisions, 1959-1965 (Box 48, Folder 13)
        Contains decisions concerning armbands, salary schedules, the rights of teachers associations to use faculty mailboxes, and strikes. 1959-65
      - SED-Commissioner's Decisions, 1965 (Box 48, Folder 14)
        Contains I information and decisions dealing with salary schedules and the need to hire school nurse teachers versus the need to hire R.N.s to administer school health services. Also contains correspondence regarding these points between Goold and Allen. 1965
      - State Education Department, 1966 (Box 48, Folder 15)
        Commissioner's Decision, Saratoga Decision. Contains material dealing with a case involving dress codes. 1966
      - SED-Commissioner's Decision, 1967 (Box 48, Folder 16)
        Deals with a claim that a teacher was forced to join a teachers association. 1967
      - SED-Commissioner's Decision, 1967 (Box 48, Folder 17)
        Contains decision re employment of school nurse teachers. 1967
      - SED-Commissioner's Decision, 1967 (Box 48, Folder 18)
        Contains decision and amicus brief filed with regard to teacher supervision of extracurricular actives. 1967
      - SED-Commissioners Decision, 1967 (Box 48, Folder 19)
        Sperling Case re maternity leave. 1967
      - SED-Commissioner's Decision, 1967 (Box 48, Folder 20)
        July 20. 1967 Abraham Wiener. Contains decision dealing with course credit and salary differentials. 1967
      - SED-Commissioner's Meeting, June 23, 1964 (Box 48, Folder 21)
        NYSTA, School Boards. General correspondence. 1964
      - SED-Dr. Crewson, 1961 (Box 48, Folder 22)
        Contains general correspondence and a memo dealing with the minimum requirement for schools. 1961
      - SED-Dr. Crewson, 1962 (Box 48, Folder 23)
        Contains newsletters, bulletins dealing with the revised state aid plan, and a memo of counsel in relation to the state aid formula. Also contains memos dealing with modernization and extension of technical education, the creation of an advisory board on teacher education, certification and practice, and the licensing of teachers in NYC. 1962